Guide to the James Lindsay Dyson papers, ca. 1933-1971
Dyson, James Lindsay papers, ca. 1933-1971
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
James Lindsay Dyson papers, ca. 1933-1971
4293
James Lindsay Dyson, 1912-
6.4 cubic ft.
Research files, card files, manuscripts, photographs, scrapbooks, notebooks, correspondence, and other papers.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Student papers, primarily laboratory and lecture notes from Cornell University; documents, notebook, and scrapbook relating to his experiences in the U.S. Army during World War II and in the Army Reserve; subject files relating to his teaching at Lafayette College and his work as a geologist; research files, card files, manuscripts, photographs, reviews, and articles on The World of Ice; research files for a projected work, The World of Water; scrapbooks; geology and ornithology field notebooks; personal correspondence and photographs; and other publications by James L. Dyson. Also, correspondence with Lolita Dyson about a scholarship established at Lafayette College in memory of her husband.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
James L. Dyson graduated from Lafayette College in 1933 and received his doctorate from Cornell University in 1938. He served as an Instructor in Geology at Cornell from 1935 to 1938 and at Colgate from 1938 to 1941. In 1947 he became Head of the Department of Geology and Geography at Lafayette College, a position he held until his death in 1967. During World War II, he served in various positions in the U.S. Army, eventually as Commanding Officer of the First Training Center in New Guinea and later on the island of Luzon in the Philippines. After the war, he remained active in the Army Reserve. He was best known for his scientific work as a geomorphologist and glaciologist, publishing a number of works on Glacier National Park and a major work, The World of Ice. He served as a Cooperating Geologist of the Pennsylvania Geological Survey, doing detailed studies of the New Bloomfield Quadrangle. He was an ardent conservationist and was also deeply concerned with the improvement of geologic education.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Student papers, primarily laboratory and lecture notes from Cornell University; documents, notebook, and scrapbook relating to his experiences in the U.S. Army during World War II and in the Army Reserve; subject files relating to his teaching at Lafayette College and his work as a geologist; research files, card files, manuscripts, photographs, reviews, and articles on The World of Ice; research files for a projected work, The World of Water; scrapbooks; geology and ornithology field notebooks; personal correspondence and photographs; and other publications by James L. Dyson. Also, correspondence with Lolita Dyson about a scholarship established at Lafayette College in memory of her husband.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Dyson, James L. (James Lindsay), 1912-1967.; Dyson, Lolita Brown.; Cornell University.; Lafayette College.; United States. Army.; Geological Survey of Pennsylvania.
Subjects:
Geology--Research.; Geology--Study and teaching.; Glaciers.; Glaciology.; Ice.; Geomorphology.; Geological surveys.; Geology--Pennsylvania--Surveys.; Ornithology.; Geologists.; College teachers.
Places:
Glacier National Park (Mont.)
Form and Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Field notes.; Scrapbooks.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
SERIES LIST
Series I. Lafayette College; Cornell University; military
Box 1
Series II. Professional subject files; World of Water
Box 2
Series III. World of Water; personal
Box 3
Series IV. World of Ice
Boxes 4, 6
Series V. Photographs-- World of Ice
Box 7
Series VI. Photographs--General
Box 7
Series VII. Scrapbooks; field notebooks: ornithology and geology
Box 5
Series VIII. Publications
Box 8
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Lafayette College; Cornell University; military
  - Lafayette College (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Lafayette College Bulletin, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Lafayette College Yearbook (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Conservation lectures (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - General economic geology (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Economic seminar (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Fossils (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Geology 500-Cement Report (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Geology 500-Coal Report (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Geophysics (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Metamorphic geology (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Optical determination of minerals (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Petrography lectures (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Petrograph lab (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Sedimentary petrography (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Sedimentary petrography lab (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Secimentary petrography notes (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Sedimentary reports (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Seismology (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Structural geology (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Structural geology (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Miscellaneous reports (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Travel (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Field notebooks, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Field notebooks (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Ph.D. thesis (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Colgate Univ. - Penn. relay watch story, 1940-1942 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Military papers, 1941-1945 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Army - Medical (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Army - Pay vouchers (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Army - OCS - Australia (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Army - General (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Army - General (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Replacement (training) depot (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Availability questionaire (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Recommendation for promotion (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Research and development subgroup (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Active duty training - Applications (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Active duty training - 1955 Ft. Knox, Ky., 1955 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Active duty training - 1956, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Active duty training - Fort Meade 1956, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - First replacement training center (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - First replacement training center (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Commendation (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Field notes, 1940, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Certificates (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Notes (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Clipping and map (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Lafayette College - Applications (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Princeton University Canada field trip (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - U.S.G.A. - Grinnell Glacier (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Birds, 1952-1958 (Box 1, Folder 52)
- Series II. Professional subject files; World of Water
  - American Alpine Club (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - American Geological Institute (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Bergethon, K. Roald (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Boyertown Report - Plates (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Geology of the site of the trout run impounding dam, Boyertown, Bucks County (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Congressmen (correspondence) (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Dyson, Elgar L. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - J. Gordon Edwards (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Encyclopedia of American Biography (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Fairchild Garden speech (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Glaciers (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Glacier recession paper (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Glacier committee (general) (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Geological Society of America (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Governors Conference (on natural beauty) (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Island Beach, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Landscape book (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Sabbatical leave (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Lectures - Correspondence with organizations (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Lectures (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Lectures (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Lectures - Slide list (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Lectures - Agents (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Middle Atlantic Track and Field Association (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - National Park Service (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - New Bloomfield - South Half (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - New Bloomfield - Write-up (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - New Bloomfield (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Philadelphia Conservationists (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Project 70 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Published - General (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Published - Glaciers (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Published - Geology (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Published - Water (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Sterling College lecture (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Stream pollution (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Sylvania uranium (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - U.S. Dept. Int. - Lamont - Syracuse (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - USGS - Denver (Geological Survey) (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Weather (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - West Virginia - Lecture (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Writings - Projected book on folded Appalachians (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Writings - Badlands (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Publications - "The Cold World" - Holiday (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Writings - Glacier National Park (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Writings - Ice-ridged moraines (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Writings on nature - Fossil-finding - Mid-Atlantic states (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Writings - Uranium at Mauch Chunk (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Water - Newspaper clippings (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - World of Water - Correspondence (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - World of Water - Manuscript - 1st draft (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - World of Water - Manuscript - 1st draft (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - World of Water - Manuscript - 1st draft (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - World of Water - Original, handwritten (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Water, Wate - Prentice Hall (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - World of Water - Publishers - Worth (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Water - Correspondence (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Standard Lime and Cement (Box 2, Folder 58)
- Series III. World of Water; personal
  - ESCP (Earth Science Curriculum Project), 1964 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Personal/professional (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Personal - Jim (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Personal - Jim (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Personal - Jim, 1957-1978 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Personal - Jim, 1957-1958 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Bibliography - Society affiliations, honors, etc. (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Personal - Jim (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Newsclippings (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Special correspondence, 1946-1949 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Special correspondence, 1946-1949 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence and personal papers (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - "Report on Geology of Potential Reservoir Sites in Leroy Township, Bradford County, Pennsylvania" by Dyson, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - JLD- Memorials (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, 1949-1966 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, 1949-1966 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - JLD - Scholarship (Lafayette) (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - JLD - most recent papers of his life (returned to donor, Dec. 1987) (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Glacier Natural History Assn. (Royalties) (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - U.S.G.A. bookplate and printing block card file: World of Water (Box 3, Folder 21)
- Series IV. World of Ice
  - 2 packages - 4x6 file cards (Box 4)
  - World of Ice - Original (1-1 to 3-50) (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - World of Ice - Original (1-1 to 3-50) (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Chapter 14 - Handwritten (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Chapters beyond 14 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Chapter 15 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Chapter 16 (related to) (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Chapter 16, handwritten (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Chapter 17, handwritten (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Outlines - used (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Art's criticism (1st copy) - read by Montgomery (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Information (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Information (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Information (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence (various publishers) (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence - Illustrations (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Reviews (complete file) (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Reviews, notices (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Publications (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Photos: Navy - Office of Information (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Photos: RCAF (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Photos: Ortenburger - Hillary Expedition (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Illustration (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - AMNH - Anthony (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Air Force - Col. degrees - Cambridge Research (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Ansel Adams - Yosemite (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Army - CRREL (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - French Gov't Tourist Office (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Geological Soc. Of America - Paper on glaciers (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Golden Books article - including manuscript (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Golden Books article (ms.) typescript copy (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - IGY - Odishaw - Crevase detector and sea ice (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Kabel - Photos (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Klosterman - Photos (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Lawrence - data (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Mackin - Photo (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - National Parks Mag. Ice Age Scientific Reserve (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - NPS Anderson (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - NPS Mt. Rainier (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - NPS Olympic (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - NPS Yosemite (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - NSF Phil Smith (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Noxon - Photo Harvard Karakoram Exped. (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Pewe Alaska (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - Sacramento Bee (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - Bob Sharp, Cal Tech (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - Swiss Tourist (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - Thornbury - photos - Indiana University (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - USGS - Davis (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - Washburn (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - Zumberge - photos (Box 4, Folder 54)
  - Alfred A. Knopf, Inc. (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Alfred A. Knopf, Inc. (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Publicity (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Congratulations (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Congratulations (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - TREOG (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Black, Robert photos (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Cal. Div. Of Highways (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Canada - Geol. Survey and Surveys Mapping Branch (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - W. S. Cooper photos (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Data Center A (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Statistics - Autographed copies, complimentary copies, publication of reviews (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Inter-library loans (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence (individuals) (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Permission and authentication (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Advance announcement (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Chapter 15 - Nature keeps the record (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Manuscript (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Manuscript (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Manuscript (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Manuscript (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Galley proof (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Galley proof (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Hugh Moore Parkway (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Lectures - Mss. And slide lists (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Lectures - Mss. and slide lists (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - Lectures - Mss. and slide lists (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Lectures - Mss. and slide lists (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - Lectures - Mss. and slide lists (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - World of Ice (Box 6, Folder 30)
  - Lafayette College - Board of Trustees campaign dinner, 1944 (Box 6, Folder 31)
  - Lafayette College - Engineering - Science Centennial Convocation, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 32)
  - ESCP Newsletters (Earth Science Curriculum Project), 1963-1966 (Box 6, Folder 33)
- Series V. Photographs-- World of Ice
  - Plates 1-4 (Box 7, Folder 33)
  - Plates 5-7 (Box 7, Folder 34)
  - Plates 9-12 (9b missing) (Box 7, Folder 35)
  - Plates 13-20 (Box 7, Folder 36)
  - Plates 22-29 (24 is also back endpaper) (Box 7, Folder 37)
  - Plates 31,32,34-36 (36 is also front paper) (Box 7, Folder 38)
  - Plates 37-42 (Box 7, Folder 39)
  - Plates 43-49 (Box 7, Folder 40)
  - Plates 50-62 (58b is missing) (Box 7, Folder 41)
  - Plates 8, 21 (Box 7, Folder 42)
  - Plate 5 (negative) (Box 7, Folder 43)
  - Plate 11a (negative) (Box 7, Folder 44)
  - Plates 48a, 57a, 58a (negatives) (Box 7, Folder 45)
- Series VI. Photographs--General
  - James Dyson, 1961 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Lafayette College faculty, 1960-1964 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Kappa Delta Rho (Lafayette College), 1933 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - James Dyson - Track (Lafayette) (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Military, 1934 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - 20th Reunion Lafayette College Class of '33 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - 30th Reunion Lafayette College Class of '33 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Christmas 1940, 1941 Dyson Family?, 1940-1941 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Unidentified (early) family portrait (reproduction) (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Photos by Dyson - Glaciers, 1940 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Photos by Dyson - all numbered (Box 7, Folder 11-20)
  - Alden Photos Sperry Glacier 1913, Clements, Agassiz (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Shepard Glacier (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - Cheney Glacier (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - Boulder Glacier (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - "Photographs - G.S.A. Paper Duplicates" (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - Campell, Stebinger photos, 1911-1914 (Box 7, Folder 26)
  - Blackfoot and Jackson Glaciers (Box 7, Folder 27)
  - World of Ice, U.S. Coast and Geodetic Survey (Box 7, Folder 28)
  - Ice Photos - unidentified glaciers (Box 7, Folder 29)
  - World of Ice, glaciers - not used (Box 7, Folder 30)
  - Color photos (Box 7, Folder 31)
  - Grinnell Glaciers (Box 7, Folder 32)
- Series VII. Scrapbooks; field notebooks: ornithology and geology
  - Many Glacier Log, 1946 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Field book - Mauch Chunk uranium, 1952-1954 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Field book - Mauch Chunk and others, 1954, 1962-1963 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Field book - Kittatinny Mts. and adjacent areas Top Rock Project (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Mining transit book (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Field book - Hercules Cement, book No. 1 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Field book, Hercules Cement, book No. 2 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Field book, Hercules Cement, book No. 3 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Field book, Hercules Cement, book No. 4 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Bird notes, 1927-1939 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Bird notes (Glacier Park), also others, 1948, 1950-1954 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Bird observations, 1952-1961 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Bird Lists, 1927-1948 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Alberta field trip (Princeton Univ.) (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Book no. 1 - Scrapbook, 1929-1957 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Photograph scrapbook (Box 5, Folder 16)
- Series VIII. Publications
  - "Ruby Gulch Gold Mining District, Little Rocky Mountains, Montana,", Mar.-Apr. 1939; Cornell University Abstracts of Theses. Accepted in Partial Satisfaction of the Requirements for the Doctor's Degree 1938. In Economic Geology, Vol XXXIV, No. 2, Mar.-Apr. 1939 (Box 8)
  - "Ice-Ridged Moraines and Their Relation to Glaciers,", Mar. 1952; American Journal of Science, Mar. 1952, Vol 250 (Box 8)
  - "Shrinkage of Sperry and Grinnell Glaciers, Glacier National Park Montana,", Jan. 1948; Geographical Review Vol. XXVIII, No. 1 Jan. 1948 (Box 8)
  - "Grinnel Glacier, Glacier National Park, Montana,", 1939; by George R. Gibson and Dyson, Vol. 50, Geological Society of America, 1939 (Box 8)
  - "Recent Glacier Recession in Glacier National Park, Montana,", Nov.-Dec. 1941; Journal of Geology, Vol. XLIX, No. 8 Nov.-Dec. 1941 (Box 8)
  - "Recession of Glaciers in Glacier National Park, Montana,", Transactions of 1940 of the American Geophysical Union (Box 8)
  - "Supergene Zinc and Lead Minerals at Balmat, N.Y." (Box 8)
  - "History and Activities of Theta Chapter, Cornell University,", Nov. 1937; by F.B. Rosevear and Dyson, Nov. 1937, The Compass of Sigma Gamma Epsilon, Vol. XVIII, No. 1 (Box 8)
  - "Relation of Stratigraphy and Structure to Uranium Occurrences Near Mauch Chunk, Pa.,", 1954; Proceedings of Pennsylvania Academy of Science, Vol. XXVIII, 1954 (Box 8)
  - "The Geologic Story of Glacier National Park,", Glacier Natural History Association Special Bulletin, No. 3, with National Park Service Department of Interior (Box 8)
  - "Permafrost - Ice Beneath the Ground,", Dec. 1962; Dec. 1962 (condensed from a chapter of The World of Ice), Science Digest (Box 8)
  - "Snowslide Erosion,", Apr. 1938; Science, Apr. 1938, Vol. 87, No. 2260 (Box 8)
  - "Snowslide Striations,", July-Aug. 1937; Journal of Geology, Vol. XLV, No. 5, July-Aug. 1937 (Box 8)
  - "Recent Glacier Recession in Glacier National Park, Montana,", Nov.-Dec. 1941; Journal of Geology, Vol. XLIX, No. 8 Nov.-Dec. 1941 (Box 8)
  - (also, other articles, reviews, articles and publications by other authors) (Box 8)